Okay בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Today's דף daf is מ', Mem, excuse
me, עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah 40. We're a little behind. We pick
up on ל"ט עמוד ב' Lamed Tet Amud Bet ומלח סלקונדרית. Umelach
Salkondarit. It is three lines before the lines get wide and we
are listing cases in the משנה Mishna which are forbidden but not
forbidden in הנאה. hana'ah. So let's find out what this interesting salt
is. So מאי מלח סלקונדרית? Mai Melach Salkondarit? What is this salt
of סלקונדרית? Salkondarit? So אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל: Amar Rav Yehuda
Amar Shmuel: מלח שכל סלקונדרי רומי אוכלין אותה, Melach shekol Salkondari Romi
ochlin osa, the salt that all of the סלקונדרי Salkondari of Rome
eat, which רש"י Rashi says means the bakers of Rome.
I will tell you that the
קורן גמרא Koren Gemara basically explains that this could come from the
word the Greek hals kondaris, which means a type of salt and
a salt that comes in large granular chunks, or they suggest sal
conditum, a salt seasoned with various herbs. Okay, and as for the
word סלקונדרי, Salkondari, which רש"י Rashi interprets as bakers, you know, they
say that it could mean people that are gathered, so a type
of salt that is like for important government officials. Okay, let's find
out what the problem is with it. תנו רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan: מלח
סלקונדרית Melach Salkondaris ששחורה אסורה, shesh’chorah asurah, if it's black it's forbidden;
לבנה מותרת, levanah muteres, if it's white it's okay. דברי רבי מאיר.
Divrei Rabbi Meir. רבי יהודה אומר: Rabbi Yehuda omer: the
opposite, לבנה אסורה שחורה מותרת, levanah asurah shesh’chorah muteres, white is forbidden,
black is okay. רבי יהודה בן גמליאל משום רבי חנניא בן גמליאל
אומר: Rabbi Yehuda ben Gamaliel mishum Rabbi Chananya ben Gamaliel omer: זו
וזו אסורה, zo vezo asurah, both are forbidden. אמר רבה בר בר
חנה אמר רבי יוחנן: Amar Rabbah bar bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan:
לדיבי דאמר לבנה אסורה, ledivei de'amar levanah asurah, according to the one
that says white is forbidden, קרבי דגים לבנים טמאים מעורבין בה, kirvei
dagim levanim teme'im meravim bah, what they do is they take some
of the innards of white fish and they mix it with the
salt. I don't know why they would do this, make it into
big blocks of salt I guess, I don't know, to congeal it
or something, who knows? Okay, לדיבי דאמר שחורה אסורה, ledivei de'amar shesh’chorah
asurah, if the black one is forbidden, קרבי דגים שחורים טמאים מעורבין
בה, kirvei dagim shechorim teme'im meravim bah, or שחורין shechorin טמאים teme'im
מעורבין בה, meravim bah, same thing except that they use black the
insides of black fish. לדיבי דאמר זו וזו אסורה, ledivei de'amar zo
vezo asurah, זה וזה מעורבין בה, zeh vezeh meravim bah, the one
that says both are forbidden feels that they use both types of
fish. אמר רבי אבהו משום רבי חנניא בן גמליאל: Amar Rabbi Abahu
mishum Rabbi Chananya ben Gamaliel: זקן אחד היה בשכונתו שהיה מחליק פניה
בשומן חזיר, zaken echad hayah beshechunato shehayah machalik paneya beshuman chazir, that
there was a certain old man in his that used to white,
you know, smear the face of this salt with the fat of
a pig. So maybe that's suggesting another reason why it might be
forbidden in the משנה. Mishna. Okay, so then the משנה Mishna ended:
הרי אלו אסורין אבל אין אסורין בהנאה, Harei elu asurin aval ein
asurin behana'ah, behold these are forbidden but not forbidden in הנאה. hana'ah.
למיעוטי מאי? Lemi'utei mai? So these are forbidden to what are you
excluding? לחזקיה LeChizkiyah למיעוטי בידוע, lemi'utei beyadu'a, for Chizkiyah it would exclude
the case that we mentioned before when you have these pickled things
if you know that you added wine then it would be forbidden
even in הנאה. hana'ah. These are forbidden only בסתמא, bestama, things similar
to this like when you know wine was added would be forbidden
even in הנאה. hana'ah. Okay, לרבי יוחנן, LeRabbi Yochanan, Rabbi Yochanan who
disagreed with that, למיעוטי מוריס וגבינת בית אונייקי, lemi'utei muris ugevina beis
unayiki, to exclude the case of this מוריס muris and this which
is again some type of a fish thing that wine was added
to and these types of cheeses from the previous משנה, Mishna, not
the one we're on, the one before that, וסתמא כרבי מאיר, ustama
k’Rabbi Meir, and it's going like רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that says
that those have a wine concern or an עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah
you know related concern and are forbidden in הנאה. hana'ah. Okay, so
now we've done things that are forbidden in הנאה, hana'ah, things that
are forbidden in אכילה, achilah, and now we do things that are
permitted in אכילה, achilah, which is pretty similar to the previous משנה
Mishna but with the key criteria changed. ואלו מותרין באכילה, Ve'elu mutarin
beachilah, the following things are permissible to be eaten: חלב שחלבו עובד
כוכבים וישראל רואהו, chalav shechalvo akum veYisrael ro'ehu, milk that was milked
by a
non-Jew as opposed to when a Jew isn't seeing him, if a
Jew is observing it's permissible.
והדבש
והדבדבניות, Vedevash vehadvidvaniyot, and honey and grape clusters, דובדבן duvdevan nowadays means
cherry but okay, grape clusters, אף על פי שמנטפין אין בהם משום
הכשר משקה. af al pi shemenatfin ein bahem mishum hachshir mashkeh. And
so this thing, excuse me, והדבש, vedevash, honey is okay and grape
clusters, even if they're dripping, that dripping grape juice does not make
it considered, it's not something that you want, you want to eat
the grapes you don't want the juice, so it's not לרצונו leratsono
and therefore the grapes do not become susceptible to becoming טמא, tamei,
not at all clear what that has to do in this משנה
Mishna where we're talking about things forbidden to be eaten or permissible
to be eaten. Okay, הכבשין שאין דרכן ליתן לתוכן יין וחומץ, Hakevashim
she'ein darkan liten letochan yayin vechometz, and pickled things that you normally
would not put יין yayin or חומץ chometz into. וטרית שאינה טרופה,
Vetarith she'einah terufah, and this וטרית, tarith, this type of a fish
that is not chopped up, so therefore when it was chopped up
you were afraid that there was other non-kosher fish mixed up with
it. וציר שיש בו דג, Vetziyar sheyesh bo dag, and this certain
type of fish brine that has these little חילפית kilvit fish, maybe
like type of, you know, sardines or something, tiny little fish. swimming
in it and when they're swimming in it then you know that
it's all like kosher ingredients, but as רש״י Rashi *Rashi* explains when
you know they're not swimming in it that but if there happens
to be the brine of non-kosher fish then these כילבית kilbis *kilbis*
will not be swimming in it, I really cannot tell you I
understand that reality, okay, so but if there are these little fish
swimming in it then it's all brine from kosher fish. The עלה
חילתית *aleh chiltis* and the the leaf of this חילתית *chiltis*, the
חילתית *chiltis* was that very sharp spice that you know that that
makes even the the stuff from the knife makes it לשבח *l'shevach*,
but here this the leaf would not be a problem. The עלה
חילתית *aleh chiltis* וזיתי גלוסקאות
המגוגלים *v'zeisei gluskaos hamugagalin*
and like cakes of olives that were rolled so like very olives
that were bunched together in these tight cakes and that they were
sort of sitting in their juices and they're you know very soft.
Okay.
And רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi. אומר *Rabbi Yossi omer* השלחים אסורין assurin,
*hashlachim asurin* החגבים הבאים hachagavim habaim מן הסלולה אסורין *hachagavim
habaim min hasalula asurin*.
Excuse me, I ran those two together. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi אומר
*Rabbi Yossi omer* השלחים אסורין *hashlachim asurin*, the שלחים *shlachim* grapes which
we'll see in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* means like the very, very
soft ones that the pits come right out of, those are forbidden
and we'll see why they're forbidden in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. Now,
new point. החגבים הבאים מן הסלולה אסורין *hachagavim habaim min hasalula asurin*,
if you have locust, you know, which are kosher locust that come
from the salesman's basket, they are forbidden because when they would put
them out in the store they would sprinkle wine over it, you
know maybe to make it smell good or something or to whatever
affect the taste, but מן ההפתק מותרים *min haheftek mutarim*, but if
they're coming from you know from the הפתק *heftek* which is the
storeroom then they are permitable permissible because then they would not sprinkle
wine and we
because the wine was only put when they were right placed in
front of the store owner. וכן לתרומה vechen litruma, אמרי *v'chen l'terumas
amarei* regarding תרומה teruma, *teruma* which we'll see what that means in
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. Okay, גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. תנינא להא דתנו רבנן
*tanina l'da d'tanu rabonon* this ברייתא Baraita *brayta* that says it if
a Jew is observing it is consistent with what we taught in
the ברייתא Baraita *brayta*. דתנו רבנן *d'tanu rabonon* we taught in the
ברייתא Baraita: *brayta* יושב ישראל בצד עדרו של עובד כוכבים *yoshev yisrael
b'tzad edro shel oved kochavim*, the Jew can sit next to the
whole flock of the non-Jew, עובד כוכבים חולב לו *oved kochavim choleiv
lo* and the non-Jew is milking and ומביא לו *v'meivi lo* and
can bring him the milk ואינו חושש *v'eino choshesh* and you don't
have to worry that non-kosher milk would be added so you see
if you're sitting and observing it's okay. Now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says like this: היכי דמי *heichi dami*? what's the case? אי דליכא
דבר טמא tamei בעדרו פשיטא pishita *ei d'leika davar tamei b'edro pshita*,
if there's no
non-kosher animals in the flock so of course it's פשיטא pishita *pshita*
okay to be sitting by, you know what's the חידוש chiddush. *chidush*?
ואי דאיכא דבר טמא tamei. בעדרו אמאי *v'ei d'ika davar tamei b'edro
ammai*, if there are non-kosher animals
around then why is
sitting good? Because it sounds like that you're sitting and you're not
actually seeing. It doesn't say that you're directly observing, it says you're
just sitting there nearby.
So so what's the פשט pshat *pshat*? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says לעולם דאיכא דבר טמא tamei, *l'olam d'ika davar tamei*. No there
is a non-kosher animal around that maybe he's milking from. דכי קאי
חזי ליה *v'ki kai chazi lei* when he's the Jew would stand
up he would see him. וכי יתיב לא חזי ליה *v'ki yasiv
lo chazi lei* when he's sitting he can't see the non-Jew. So
that's why and the חידוש *chidush* of the ברייתא baraita, *brayta* is
that sitting is enough, you don't literally need רואהו *ro'ehu* which is
what the משנה mishna, *Mishna* implied, sitting is enough because you're in
a position that you could always stand up and see it any
moment. לא חזי ליה *lo chazi lei* מהו דתימא *mah d'teima* let's
thought כיון דיתיב לא חזי ליה ניחוש דלמא מערב בה *kivan d'yasiv
lo chazi lei neichosh d'dilma mairiv bei* since when he's sitting he
can't see him let's be concerned that he'll bring non-kosher milk and
mix it up. קא משמע לן כיון דכי קאי חזי ליה *kamashmalan
kivan d'ki kai chazi lei* this teaches you that since when the
Jew stands he can see the
non-Jew so מירתת *irsas mirsas* ולא מערב *v'lo mairiv* the non-Jew is
afraid and won't mix in. Okay, so that for sitting by and
just not even observing every moment is okay. Now I should mention
that there's a major debate ספרדים *Sephardim* and אשכנזים Ashkenazim *Ashkenazim*, you
know this is the issue of חלב ישראל *Chalav Yisrael* of what
is the story if there is no real concern of non-kosher animal
milk, there's no non-kosher animals on the whole farm. Okay, so you
could say well the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says if there's no non-kosher
animals it's פשיטא *pshita*, so that sounds like the גזירה *gezeira* doesn't
apply. But the response back to that is no, it's saying if
there's no non-kosher animals it's פשיטא *pshita* that a Jew sitting nearby
makes it permitted, but you still would need the Jew sitting nearby
is the counter argument. So that is the debate. So ספרדים *Sephardim*
basically always felt that if there's no concern of non-kosher milk there's
no problem of חלב ישראל *Chalav Yisrael*, אשכנזים *Ashkenazim* felt no you
always need a Jew observing it even if there are no non-kosher
animals. So how is it that you know those who are not
מקפיד *makpid* on חלב ישראל *Chalav Yisrael* and follow the אשכנזי *Ashkenazi*
פסק *psak* what do we do? So this was רב משה *Rav
Moshe's* חידוש *chidush*, רב משה *Rav Moshe* basically said since right now
not only is it that they don't happen to be non-kosher animals
but there really would be consequences you know you get
USDA stamp of approval, you'd have to pay fines, there are consequences,
you might want to throw in that there's absolutely no financial incentive,
it's only a financial disincentive if they got found out that they
were mixing in other milks. So therefore, it's obvious. So what? It's
also,
so because it's obvious, it's אנן סהדי. It's like we're all witness
to the fact and that makes it as if ישראל רואהו. Yisrael
ro-eihu. So Rav Moshe says even according to the אשכנזים that generally
require that it's not enough that there's no non-kosher animal, require the
formal presence of a Jew to observe it, nowadays it's so clear
and so obvious that it's like we have that. So that's רב
משה'ס Rav Moshe's חידוש. Okay, והדבש. Ve-hadvash. So let's take a look,
honey. דבש למה ניחוש לה? Dvash le-mah neichush lah? What should we
be concerned about when it comes to honey?
Meaning what? There's nothing to be concerned about. אי משום ערובי, Ee
mishum eruvey, if we're afraid maybe they mix in some wine, סרויי
מסרי, misrei misrei, it'll spoil, they wouldn't do it. אי משום בשולי
עובדי כוכבים, Ee mishum bishuley ovdey kochavim, if we're afraid that maybe
they cooked the honey and it's בשול עכו"ם, bishul akum, נאכל כמו
שהוא חי, ne'echal kemo shehu chai, it could be eaten raw, not
a problem. אי משום געולי עובדי כוכבים, Ee mishum gi'uley ovdey kochavim,
maybe when they cook the honey to get out the wax, they
cooked it in some type of a pot that gave that was
used for טרפה. treif.
So no, נותן טעם לפגם הוא ומותר. noten ta'am lifgam hu umutar.
It would that whatever if they cooked anything before it would only
give a bad taste to the honey, it would be permissible. This
גמרא Gemara and other גמרות Gemoros that we're learning that assume that
if you used a non-kosher pot it's giving a bad
taste leads to the assumption never stated in the גמרא Gemara but
stated in תוספות Tosafot here, stated in the ראשונים Rishonim that סתם
כלים של עכו"ם אינם בני יומן. stam keilim shel akum einam bnei
yoman. We assume that the pots of non-Jews are not בני יומן
bnei yoman and the סתם stam taste we assume comes from them
is a bad taste בדיעבד, bedi'avad, not to allow you to use
it לכתחילה. lechatchila. תוספות Tosafot actually says that it's like a ספק
ספיקא. sfek sfeika. Maybe they're today's pot and maybe they're yesterday's pot.
If it's yesterday's, it's נותן טעם לפגם noten ta'am lifgam and definitely.
And even if it's today's, maybe it was cooked with something that
would give a bad taste. That's how תוספות Tosafot explains the assumption
that we always assume that the pots are not a problem בדיעבד.
bedi'avad. Okay, והדבדבניות, Ve-hadvadvaniyot, which are grape clusters. אף על פי שמתזפות
אין בהם משום הכשר משקה. Af al pi shemitatfot ein bahem mishum
hechsher mashkeh. רמי ני Remini says, well ask you, הבוצר לגת, habotzer
legat, if somebody is harvesting grapes and is going to be pressing
them to make grape juice to turn into wine, שמאי אומר הוכשר,
Shammai omer huchshar, the grapes have become and some liquid drips out,
susceptible to becoming
טמא tamei, because that's the juice, you want the juice out of
the grapes. Okay, הלל אומר לא הוכשר, Hillel omer lo huchshar, and
הלל Hillel says that it has not become
susceptible, and הלל Hillel wound up agreeing to שמאי. Shammai. So why
there is it susceptible and here not? And the answer is relatively
obvious. גמרא Gemara says התם קא בעי ליה למשקה. hatam ka ba-ei
lei lemashkeh. There it's saying that you're harvesting them to make to
press them, you want the liquid. הכא לא קא בעי ליה למשקה.
hacha lo ka ba-ei lei lemashkeh. Here you want to eat the
grapes so you don't want the liquid to come out. Okay,
וטרס שאינה טרופה, Vetaras she-eina trufa, this טרס taras fish that is
not like chopped up because and then you can see that it's
this טרס taras fish and it's kosher and nothing else is mixed
up. תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan, two lines from the bottom, our Rabbis
taught: איזהו טרס שאינה טרופה? eizehu taras she-eina trufa? What consists not
chopped up, meaning visible enough that you could identify it? כל שראש
ושדרה ניכר, kol she-rosh ve-shidra nikar, that you can identify the head
and the spine and see that they are from this טרס taras
fish. Okay, now רש"י Rashi says, if you look at רש"י, Rashi,
כל שראש ושדרה ניכרין kol she-rosh ve-shidra nikarin של כל דג ודג,
shel kol dag vadag, that you can see every fish, you can
see the head and the spine, because if it was just some
of them then you'd have to be worried about the others. Okay,
ואיזהו ציר שיש בו דגה? ve-eizehu tzir she-yesh bo daga? And what
is going to the next case of our משנה, this type of
fish brine that has these כלבית kilbit fish swimming in it, which
somehow indicate that the brine is from kosher fish? So what's that
reality? כל שכלבית אחת או שתי כלביות שוטטות בו. kol she-kilbit achat
o shtei kilbiyot shotetot bo. דף ל"ט עמוד א'. Daf lamed tet
amud aleph. As long as anything that one or two of these
כלביות kilbiyot are swimming in it. So the גמרא Gemara asks the
obvious question: השתא כלבית אחת אמרת שרי, hashtah kilbit achat amart sharei,
if one is enough to make it permissible, שתי כלביות מבעיא? shtei
kilbiyot mibaya? Why do you have to say two?
So לא קשיא, lo kashya, it's not difficult: כאן בפתוחות כאן בסתומות.
kan bif tuchot kan bistumot. It depends if the barrel is open
or closed. So there's a little debate of רש"י Rashi and תוספות,
Tosafot, but I'll tell you רש"י Rashi says, if it's open, you
would need two of these כלבית kilbit fishes because if there was
only one, well maybe one of them somehow flopped its way out
of the barrel. So you need two.
Excuse me, I think I, excuse me, I was anticipating the next
גמרא Gemara that's going to be about an open barrel then possibly
coming out. Here according to רש"י Rashi it's about an open barrel
and possibly coming in. If it's an open barrel maybe I don't
know somehow this fish flopped in from somewhere else. I'm not sure
why somebody else would be carrying some brine with fish that would
fall into this barrel, but anyway that's what רש"י Rashi says, but
if it's so therefore you need two to show that it's not
just chance. that there's this one כילבית in it, but if it's
closed then obviously it came from the brine, it was only within
the brine itself, and one is sufficient. Okay. So now the גמרא
Gemara says like this: איתמר itmar was taught, רב הונא אמר Rav
Huna amar עד שיהא ראש ושדרה ניכר. ad sheyehei rosh veshidra nikar.
If you want to permit a fish that you and interestingly you're
not able to inspect it in terms of the fins and the
scales, so here we see that certain fish could be identified in
ways without the fins and scales, by the head and the spine
it was very identifiable. So he says you need to see both.
Okay. ורב נחמן אמר veRav Nachman amar או ראש או שדרה. o
rosh o shidra. רב נחמן Rav Nachman says one is sufficient if
it's identifiable by just one of them. Okay, by the way to
give you an analogy, right, can you go ahead and buy a
salmon steak or a salmon
fillet, I guess a steak might have some of the skin, it
would have the skin on it. But a salmon fillet, right? Do
you say that like look sometimes you can see that it's salmon
even if you're not directly seeing, you know, the what do you
call it, you know,
the fins and the scales? So the question is do you need
to see both things to identify or is one enough? So מתיב
רב עוקבא בר חמא. metiv Rav Ukva bar Chama. רב עוקבא בר
חמא Rav Ukva bar Chama challenged these positions. ובדגים, uvedagim, you know
we teach in חולין Chullin that when it comes to fish כל
שיש לו סנפיר וקשקשת, kol sheyesh lo snapir vekaskeset, that the סימן
siman is, you know, is fins and scales. And it does not
say you can look at the head or the, you know, or
the spine. It seems like those are the only סימנים. simanim. So
אמר אביי amar Abaye says אביי Abaye כי תניא ההיא בארעא ופומדא
ki tanya hahi be'ara ufumda דדמי רישייהו לטמאין. dedami reisheihu letimein. No,
no, no. Those are certain types of fish that the heads are
you can't tell just by looking at the heads. So there the
only סימן siman is the fins and scales. I mean it's not
much of a question, fins and scales is what's mentioned in the
תורה, Torah, but it's saying the reason no other סימנים simanim are
mentioned is because there are some fish that heads that looking at
the heads or maybe looking at the spine would not be good
enough. So therefore you have to look at the fins and scales.
But with this תירוץ terutz that does suffice. Okay. אמר רב יהודה
משמיה דעולא amar Rav Yehuda mishmei deUlla מחלוקת לטבול בצירן. machlokes litbol
betziran. The debate of do you need to see both the head
and the spine or just one is if you want to dip
into the like juices that come out of it, the fish oil.
אבל בגופן aval begufan if you want to eat the fish itself
דברי הכל אסור divrei hakol assur עד שיהא ראש ושדרה ניכר ad
sheyehei rosh veshidra nikar you have to see both. Now תוספות Tosafot
asks the obvious question. What difference does it make? It's both דאורייתא,
de'oraisa, you know, even the stuff, the juices that come out. We
have a principle טעם כעיקר דאורייתא. ta'am ke'ikar de'oraisa. You know the
ציר tzir of non-kosher fish is also non-kosher, the milk of non-kosher
animals is non-kosher. So why can you be more lenient if you're
just dealing with the ציר? tzir? So תוספות Tosafot says well it
would be a case that it was mixed up with like water
and therefore מדאורייתא mide'oraisa you would say בטל ברוב. batel berov. Okay,
that you would go so technically it would be בטל batel even
though דרבנן derabbanan it would not be בטל batel anyway and that's
why we would be willing to be more lenient. But not clear,
that's somewhat of an אוקימתא. okimta. Okay. אמר רבי זירא amar Rabbi
Zeira מעיקרא הוינא מטבילנא בצירן. me'ikara havina matbilna betziran. I originally would
dip in the ציר, tzir, I assumed that everybody agreed with the
ציר, tzir, only one סימן siman was necessary.
כיוון דשמענא להא דאמר רב יהודה משמיה דעולא keivan deshmana leha de'amar
Rav Yehuda mishmei deUlla מחלוקת לטבול בצירן machlokes litbol betziran that the
debate is about dipping in the ציר, tzir, אבל בגופן דברי הכל
אסור aval begufan divrei hakol assur but when it comes to the
body everybody says it's forbidden, I thought they were debating about eating
the fish itself, now I hear that they're debating about the ציר,
tzir, so in that case I'm going to be מחמיר machmir and
עד שיהא ראש ושדרה ניכר ad sheyehei rosh veshidra nikar until you
see both the head and the שדרה shidra like the position that
is מחמיר. machmir. Okay.
I'm sorry, I didn't finish the line. עד שיהא ראש ושדרה ניכר
בצירן נמי לא מטבילנא. ad sheyehei rosh veshidra nikar betziran nami lo
matbilna.
Until both the head and the spine are ניכר nikar I won't
even dip in the ציר. tzir. Okay. אמר רב פפא amar Rav
Papa says רב פפא Rav Papa הלכתא עד שיהא ראש ושדרה ניכר
hilchata ad sheyehei rosh veshidra nikar like the point we just ended
on, that even when it comes just to the ציר tzir you
have to have both the head and the spine visible if you're
going to identify it without the fins and scales. שבכל אחת ואחת
shebechol achas ve'achas and here the רש״י Rashi that we this was
what רש״י was quoting before, of each one, because if even one
is not, then that one might be something else. מיתיבי meisivei I'll
challenge you on this that you need to be able to identify
every single one. חתיכות שיש בהן סימן chatichot sheyesh bahen siman if
you have pieces of fish presumably and you have a סימן siman
on them and you can sort of see you know the fins
and scales let's say. Okay, one minute. ואם יש סימן באחת מהן.
ve'im yesh siman be'achat mehen. I'm sorry, I skipped the line. בין
בכולן
בין במקצתן bein bechulan bein bemiktzatan
whether you can see the סימן siman on all of them or
only on some of them, ואפילו באחת מהן ve'afillu be'achat mehen even
if only one out of the hundred שבין כולן מותרות shebein kulan
mutarot they're all permissible. So this sounds like, you know, let's say
you got a hundred pieces of fillet and you have one piece
that has the skin on it, you can base yourself on that
one piece with the skin to assume that all the rest are
the same type of fish. That's a pretty big קולא. kula. I
mean there's some logic to it, presumably people, you know, they chop
it up and they sell it all together, but still, you know,
that says that you actually actually do not need to identify for
each one. ומעשה umaise there was a story בעובד כוכבים אחד be'oveid
kochavim echad with a certain non-Jew שהביא גרב של חתיכות sheheivi gerev
shel chatichot he brought like you know this container of pieces of
fish ונמצא סימן באחת מהן venimtza siman be'achat mehen and there was
one of them was obvious that it was a kosher fish והתיר
רבן גמליאל את הגרב כולו vehitir Rabban Gamliel et hagerev kulo and
he permitted everything in the entire container. Okay so so doesn't that
show you that even one is enough then you can assume that
the rest are of the same type? So the גמרא Gemara says
תרגמה רב פפא targema Rav Pappa רב פפא Rav Pappa explained it
כשחתיכות שוות. keshechatichot shaveiot.
No no no no when the pieces are equal. Now what does
equal mean? So רש"י Rashi says you know what equal means is
that it's almost like a puzzle, you can fit them together and
you can see that they come from the same fish. You know
you might have wanted to say that it actually meant when they
are like you know chopped up and they seem to indicate that
they all underwent a similar process of being chopped, but that is
not what רש"י Rashi says. He says that you can fit the
pieces together and you see they all come from one fish. And
the גמרא says אי הכי מאי למימרא ee hachi mai lemimra if
so then it's obvious, and that works with רש"י's Rashi's explanation because
the possible idea that they just look similar would not say that
it's obvious. Okay but if you can fit them all together obviously
it's all מותר. mutter. So no מהו דתימא ניחוש דילמא אירמי, mahu
deteima neichosh dilma irmi, קמ"ל. kamashmalan. No
maybe one of these pieces is not from this fish and it
looks like it fits but it doesn't really fit. So this is
teaching me I don't have to worry about that. Okay
ההיא ארבא hahi arba so basically though you need to identify every
fish or to be able to actually actively see that they all
that they're all of the same fish. ההיא ארבא hahi arba there
was a boat דצחנתא detzachanta
which was carrying these like these like fish salted fish דאתי לסכרא
de'ati leSichra that came to the city of Sichra. נפק רב הונא
בר חיננא nafak Rav Huna bar Chinana so רב הונא בר חיננא
Rav Huna bar Chinana went out וחזא בה קלפי vechaza bei kilpei
and he saw that there were some you know scales mixed up
with the fish ושריה vesharayei and he permitted it. So that's another
example of saying that if you see something okay you can assume
they're all of the same type, and again this so similar to
what the פשט of that earlier teaching was, and once again we're
going to get a pushback. So אמר ליה רבא amar lei Rava
so רבא Rava said to him ומי איכא דשרי כי האי גוונא
umi ika deshayei ki hai gavna באתרא דשכיחי כלפי? be'atra deshchichei kilpei?
So is there anybody who would permit this in a place in
which scales are like you know are like common?
Meaning there are a lot of fish around here that have scales
and you know and there could have been scales that are in
this you know that are in this boat that from previous from
other fish and from the last time it was used from other
places like how can you assume that these scales came from these
fish? All right, you could also say maybe some of the fish
had scales and others did not. But anyway, how do you extrapolate?
נפיק שיפורא דרבא ואסר. nafik shipura deRava ve'asar. So רבא's Rava's shofar
went out, announcement went out, and he forbade it. Says don't listen
to him, it's טרייף. traif. So okay ושיפורא דרב הונא בר חיננא
veshipura deRav Huna bar Chinana but רב הונא בר חיננא Rav Huna
bar Chinana was not you know to be to be silenced, his
shofar went out, his announcement went out ושרי vesharei and he permitted.
אמר רב ירמיה מדיפתי לדידי אמר לי רב פפי amar Rav Yirmiyah
miDiphti ledidi amar li Rav Pappi
so now we're still a little bit troubled like how did he
permit given that we've said before you're really not allowed to extrapolate.
So he said so רב ירמיה מדיפתי Rav Yirmiyah miDiphti said that
רב פפי Rav Pappi said to me כי שרא רב הונא בר
חיננא בצירא ki shara Rav Huna bar Chinana betzira אבל בגופם לא
aval begufam lo even when he permitted it was only
the ציר, tzir, not the actual fish itself. And we already discussed
how תוספות Tosafot suggests that that could have been a little more
lenient. אמר רב אשי לדידי אמר לי רב פפי amar Rav Ashi
ledidi amar li Rav Pappi no, רב פפי Rav Pappi said to
me as opposed to what רב ירמיה Rav Yirmiyah was quoting what
רב פפי Rav Pappi said, here רב אשי Rav Ashi is saying
no רב פפי Rav Pappi said to me כי שרא רב הונא
בר חיננא ki shara Rav Huna bar Chinana when did רב הונא
בר חיננא Rav Huna bar Chinana permit? אפילו בגופם afilu begufam even
the bodies themselves, ואנא ve'ana so therefore he really was prepared to
extrapolate and permit, ואנא ve'ana and I לא מיסר אסרינא lo meisar
asreina I'm not prepared to officially announce that they're forbidden even though
רבא Rava was saying that, דקאמר לי רב פפי dekamar li Rav
Pappi because רב פפי Rav Pappi said to me that they were
permissible even if I feel uncomfortable with that ruling. ולא מישרא שרינא
velo mishra shareina but I'm not I'm also not prepared to permit
דאמר רב יהודה משמיה דעולא de'amar Rav Yehuda mishmeih deUlla because we
said before when it came to like one סימן siman or two
סימנים simanim מחלוקת בצירן machloket betziran אבל גופן דברי הכל עד דאיכא
רישא ושדרא ניכרא לכל אחד ואחד. aval gufan divrei hakol ad de'ika
reisha veshidra nikra lechol echad ve'echad.
He said that you needed to when it came to eating the
the body itself, you know, you needed to have the head and
the whatever and the spine
recognized of every single one. So meaning א' alef here we're eating
the body itself and we have to be more מחמיר machmir but
ב' bet that is a teaching that you are not allowed to
extrapolate. Okay, so we don't know exactly, you know, obviously those that
say that it's אסור assur seem to have the much more dominant
voice. Okay, second wide line. יתיב רב חיננא בר אידי קמיה דרב
אדא בר אהבה yativ Rav Chinana bar Idi kameih deRav Adda bar
Ahava so רב חיננא בר אידי Rav Chinana bar Idi was sitting
in front of רב אדא בר אהבה Rav Adda bar Ahava יתיב
וקאמר. yativ veka'amar. עובד כוכבים שהביא ארבא מלאה חביות oveid kochavim sheheivi
arba mele'ah chaviyot a non-Jew that brings a boat filled with barrels
ונמצא קילביס באחת מהן venimtza kilbis be'achat mehen and it fish brine...
ונמצא קילביס באחת מהן venimtza kilbis be'achat mehen and it found this...
obviously one of them so again it's a question similarly about extrapolating
to the others. Now תוספות *Tosafot* says כלבית *kilvis* doesn't have to
mean one כלבית *kilvis*, it could be multiple כלביות *kilviot*, however many
are needed, but can we now extrapolate to the other barrels? פתוחות
כולן מותרות *ptuchot kulan mutarot*, if they're open then they're all permitted.
Why? Even if you don't see the כלבית *kilvis* in the others.
So here's where רש"י *Rashi* said, because you're afraid, because, you know,
again from one you can extrapolate and you assume that if it's
open, it means that there was, maybe there was כלבית *kilvis* and
the כלבית *kilvis* came out. Lack of כלבית *kilvis* is not an
evidence that it's טמא *tamei*. Presence of a כלבית *kilvis* is an
evidence that it's כשר kosher *kosher*. Okay, so if it was in
one of them you can extrapolate and if it's open you can
explain why it might have fallen out. So again, that's seeming to
allow extrapolation. סתומות היא מותרת וכולן אסורות *stumot hi muteret v'kulan assurot*.
If they're, if they're sealed, then only this one is permissible, the
other are forbidden because you don't have a כלבית *kilvis* in the
others and you can't have an explanation that they were there and
they flew, and they went away. Okay, אמר Amar, ליה *amar lei*,
so he said to him, so so that was what you know
רב חנינא *Rav Chinena* was saying in front of רב אדא בר
אהבה *Rav Adda bar Ahava*. He said to him מנא לך הא
*minalach ha*, where do you know this from? מתלתא קראי שמיע לי
*mitlata karai shmia lei*, he said I didn't make it up, I
heard it from three פסוקים *psukim*, meaning three great rabbis: מרב ושמואל
ורבי יוחנן *meiRav u'Shmuel v'Rabbi Yochanan*. Okay,
so that's interesting. Now there seems to be some major opinions, at
least in some cases, you can extrapolate. אמר רב ברונא אמר רב
*amar Rav Bruna amar Rav*, said רב ברונא *Rav Bruna* in the
name of רב *Rav*: קרבי דגים ועוברן *kirvei dagim v'ubaran*, the innards
of fish and their pregnancy, like their roe, עוברן *ubaran* is a
word for their roe, you know the fish eggs, either found inside-
presumably inside of the fish, and that's why it's called עוברן *ubaran*,
you know their, their fetuses as it were. Okay, but we're talking
about roe. אין נקחין אלא ella, מן המומחה *ein nikchin ella min
hamumche*. You can only buy from the expert, from somebody that you
can trust because, you know, there's no סימנים simanim *simanim*, there's no
fins and scales, so therefore you have to be able to have
somebody who, you know, is going to, you know, who you can
trust is not going to claim that it is from a כשר
*kosher* fish when it is not. Okay. רמי ליה עולא לרבי דוסתאי
*rami lei Ulla l'Rabbi Dostai*, so עולא *Ulla* challenged רבי Rabbi דוסתאי
*Rabbi Dostai*- showed a contradiction to רבי דוסתאי *Rabbi Dostai*, meaning he
threw things- contradicted one another. דמבי *d'mibei*, from בי *be*, מידי דאמר
רב קרבי דגים ועוברן אין נקחין אלא מן המומחה *midei d'amar Rav
kirvei dagim v'ubaran ein nikchin ella min hamumche*, since he said that
you can only buy them from the expert, מכלל דדג טמא אית
ליה עובר *michlal d'dag tamei it lei ubar*, so presumably if there's
a concern about buying roe from a non-expert, it shows that you
can get roe from, you know, a- you know, from a non-כשר
*kosher* fish. And low- and you know, standard roe is from non-כשר
*kosher* fish, from sharks and sturgeon I believe. Okay, so why is
that a problem? ורמיניהי *u'raminihi*, I'll challenge you. דג טמא משריץ *dag
tamei mashritz*, we have a teaching in בכורות *Bechorot* that non-כשר *kosher*
fish, you know, sort of gestate their children inside their bodies. דג
טהור מטיל ביצים *dag tahor matil beitzim*, and כשר *kosher* fish always
do it outside their bodies and they lay eggs. By the way,
not true that this is only כשר *kosher* fish, sharks lay eggs,
other, other types of non-כשר *kosher* fish also lay eggs. Anyway, okay,
but if
that's- but from your point that you need to buy roe from
an expert, that would seem to say that non-כשר *kosher* fish lay
eggs. This teaching says that only כשר *kosher* fish lay eggs. So
the גמרא *Gemara* says סמי מכאן ועוברן *sami mikan v'ubaran*. Okay, take
the word עוברן *ubaran* out. You're right, roe you don't need an
expert, that's only from כשר *kosher* fish. אמר ליה רב זירא לא
תסמי *amar lei Rav Zeira lo tismi*. No, no, no, no, no.
Do not erase it. תרווייהו מטילי ביצים נינהו *traivaihu matilei beitzim ninhu*.
Both כשר *kosher* fish and non-כשר *kosher* fish have roe. אלא זה
משריץ מבחוץ וזה משריץ מבפנים *ella zeh mashritz mibachutz v'zeh mashritz mibifnim*.
But one of them has- the- the eggs are on the inside
and the other, you know, the eggs are on the outside. So
if you're talking about the roe, you open up the fish, you
will find a cluster of eggs both in כשר *kosher* fish and
non-כשר *kosher* fish. However, you know, and so the word משריץ *mashritz*
of non-כשר *kosher* fish doesn't mean that there are no eggs, it
just means it doesn't deposit the eggs and you know move away
from them. Sort of like a chicken, there's a scientific word for
animals that lay their eggs outside their body. So both of them
have eggs. כשר *kosher* fish lay their eggs outside their body. Non-כשר
*kosher* fish have their eggs inside their body. Okay, so that explains
the ברייתא baraita: *braita* that distinguishes כשר *kosher* and non-כשר *kosher*, but
it's also why you need an expert for roe because both כשר
*kosher* and non-כשר *kosher* do have eggs. By the way, still not
true. You know, non-כשר *kosher* fish, there are non-כשר *kosher* fish that-
you know- aquatic animals that still lay their eggs outside their body,
like certain types of shark. Okay, anyway, but now we have at
least explained that there's roe that's not כשר *kosher*, and that's why
you need an expert. Okay, so now the גמרא *Gemara* says like
this: למה לי מומחה mumcha? *lama lei mumche*? Why do you need
an expert? לובדוק בסימנין *livdok b'simanin*? Why can't you just look at,
like, you know, identifying marks on the actual eggs themselves? Now you
didn't know that there are identifying marks on the eggs themselves, but
let's take a look. דתניא ותנא ברייתא: baraita, כסימני ביצים כך סימני
דגים. K'simanei beitzim kach simanei dagim. The same way there are indicators
of eggs like from animals, from mammals, whether they are or I
don't know mammals anyway from, excuse me, not mammals, from various birds.
Thank you. There are indicating marks from various birds whether they are
from kosher birds or non-kosher birds, כך סימני דגים kach simanei dagim
there are similarly indicators about fish.
We aren't yet up to eggs. So the same way there are
indicators of bird eggs whether they're kosher or not, there are indicators
of fish. So the גמרא says: סימני דגים סלקא דעתך? simanei dagim
salka da'atach? Do you really think that this means סימנים simanim
characteristics of fish that the ברייתא is being מחדש m'chadesh to me
that fish have ways of identifying them, identifying marks? סימני דגים סנפיר
וקשקשת כתיב בהו. simanei dagim snapir v'kaskeset ksiv behu. You don't need
a ברייתא to say, "Ah, the same way you can tell eggs
there's also a way to tell fish." Of course you can tell
fish. Fish is what the תורה Torah says is fins and scales.
אלא, so here's how you must read the ברייתא: כסימני ביצים, k'simanei
beitzim,
the same way there's identifying characteristics of eggs from kosher birds as
opposed to from non-kosher birds, כך סימני עוברי דגים. kach simanei uvrei
dagim. Similarly there are identifying characteristics for the eggs—and that by the
way makes sense, the comparison, egg and eggs—of kosher fish. ואלו הן
סימני ביצים, v'elu hein simanei beitzim, and the following are the ways
to identify kosher
eggs: כסא קודרת
ואגוגלת kasa koderet v'agugelet anything that is rounded and narrow at the
top. So it goes to the top to more of a point
and it's more rounded at the bottom, it's not perfectly spherical. ראש
אחד
כד וראש אחד חד, rosh echad kad v'rosh echad chad, one side
is wide and one side is top is narrow.
And that definitely is what a normal chicken egg looks like. Go
to your fridge and check it out.
טהורה, tehorah, that's kosher. שני ראשיה חדים shenei rasheiha chadim if both
of them come to more of a point או שני ראשיה כדין
o shenei rasheiha kadin or both of them are wide, טמאה, temeiah,
that is
טמא. חלמון מבחוץ
וחלבון מבפנים, chelmon mibachutz v'chelbon mibifnim, if it has
the yolk on the outside and the white on the inside, טמאה,
temeiah, not kosher. חלבון מבחוץ וחלמון מבפנים, chelbon mibachutz v'chelmon mibifnim, if
it's the white on the outside and the yolk on the inside,
טהורה, tehorah, that's kosher. חלבון וחלמון מעורבין זה בזה chelbon v'chelmon me'uravin
zeh bazeh if they are mixed up,
they're not distinct within the egg, זו היא ביצת השרץ zu hee
beitzas hasheretz that is a ביצה beitzah from a rodent or whatever,
and that's also not kosher. Okay, so now we don't know what
are the סימנים simanim of the kosher eggs of fish. Like does
it mean that there are סימנים simanim just like there are by
bird eggs but they're different, or does it mean the same? Obviously
it's not referring to the yolk and the white. It's referring to
the wide and the narrow. Not clear. But anyway the point is,
why is this relevant? It's relevant because I skipped a line before,
apologies. So if you go and look up
seven lines before the end of the page,
right before it introduced these סימנים simanim and it said: למה לי
מומחה לבדוק בסימנים? lamma lee mumcha livdok be-simanim?
Who needs a מומחה? mumcha, Why can't we just check for the
characteristics, for the identifying marks? So the גמרא first said who needs
a מומחה, mumcha. isn't there only roe in kosher fish? It says
no, both kosher and non-kosher fish have roe, but kosher fish lay
their eggs outside the body, non-kosher fish only in the body. Not
true but okay. Anyway, but both kosher and non-kosher fish have roe,
that's why you need a מומחה. mumcha? And then the גמרא says:
Okay, but who needs a מומחה? Why don't we look at the
identifiable characteristics? So אמר רבא amar Rava last
line on מ"א ע"א: mem aleph amud aleph:
כשנימוחו, keshenimochu, we're talking that the eggs are all melted and clumped
together and you can no longer
see them distinctly and that's why you cannot go by the סימנים
and you need to trust the expert. ולרבי דימי מבירי דאמר סמו
מכאן עוברין, u'l'rebi Dimi mi-Biri d'amar semu mikan uvrin, and according to
Rebi Dimi from Biri that said take this whole idea of roe
out of the ברייתא, so
which seems to say that he feels like you don't need an
expert and all roe is kosher, so how could that be? והתניא
v'hatanya top of מ"א ע"ב, mem aleph amud beis, didn't we teach
in a ברייתא: כסימני ביצים כך סימני עוברי דגים? k'simanei beitzim kach
simanei uvrei dagim? Once we edited the ברייתא, it said just like
there are indicators on bird's eggs, there are indicators on fish roe.
So it shows you that fish roe needs an indicator, so why
did he feel like you did not need an expert?
The גמרא says: לאו תירוצא היא. lav tirutza hee. מתרצנא כך סימני
קרבי דגים mitaretzna kach simanei kirvei dagim
the same way there are indicating marks on eggs, there are indicators
for the innards of fish. Okay, but he would claim that you
do roe is always kosher and you don't need indicators. Okay, we
do not pasken that way. Okay, והיכי משכחת לה בסימני קרבי דגים
שיחד וחד? v'heichi mishkachat lah besimanei kirvei dagim sheikad v'chad?
So where is it that you have by the innards of fish
that you have these same simanim about being like wide and narrow?
So by the way, the Gemara here is making it clear that
when it says just like this so like this, it really means
not like there are simanim, but that it actually is the same
simanim. So the same way the simanim of bird eggs is wide
at the bottom and narrow at the top, similarly the simanim of
roe of fish eggs is wide at the bottom and narrow at
the top. Again, I don't know if that is true, I've had
salmon roe and it looks completely spherical to me. But anyway, but
now that the Gemara understands that that is exactly the simanim, if
we're going to edit the Braita to say that it's not about
roe but it's about their innards, what type of innards are we
looking at in terms of like wide and narrow? So the Gemara
says: משכחת לה בשלפוחא mishkachat lah bishalpucha
which is the bladder inside the fish, the swim bladder of the
fish and presumably that also can be wide at one side and
narrow at the next. Okay, אם אין שם מומחה מאי? im ein
sham mumcheh mai? So what we have said is you need an
expert because roe can be from non-kosher fish, maybe there's a way
to be able to identify it, but anyway the ruling is you
need an expert. And if there is no expert, what can you
do? Let's so, אמר רב יהודה כיוון דאמר אני מלחתים מותרין. amar
Rav Yehuda keivan d'amar ani melachtim mutarin.
If the fish guy is telling you I salted the fish, I
took these eggs out, then even if he's not somebody that you
have already established trustworthy and you know that he's going to tell
you the truth,
properly identify the eggs, okay if somebody's a middleman they might not
properly identify the eggs, but if he is claiming that he actually
is the actual person that processed them themselves, then you can trust
him. People will stand behind their words. רב נחמן אמר עד שיאמר
אלו דגים ואלו קרביהם. Rav Nachman amar ad sheyomar elu dagim v'elu
kirvehen. No,
you have to be able to say these are the fish and
these are their innards or their roe, meaning it's not enough that
he claims he was the one that removed the innards and roe,
he has to be able to show you them and then you'll
see oh those are kosher fish. Okay, so maybe you won't be
able to directly know that the innards were taken from the fish,
but you see gutted fish and you see this stuff, then you
can believe him. אמר ליה רב יהודה לאדא דיילא כיוון דאמר אני
מלחתים
מותרין. amar lei Rav Yehuda l'Ada Dayala keivan d'amar ani melachtim mutarin.
So Rav Yehuda taught to Ada his attendant, as long as the
seller says I salted them, that's enough, you don't have to have
him go ahead and like show you the fish. Okay, that is
the end of the stuff about the fish that are permissible when
it has the kils and the tarit when it's not chopped up.
ועל השחולתית v'al hashchultit now, the leaf of this chultit plant, which
the plant itself, the seed itself is very sharp and therefore it
can absorb taste and it would be a good taste from non-kosher
knives, but the leaf is okay. פשיטא obviously, it's just a leaf.
לא נצרכה אלא לקורטים שבה. lo nitzrecha ela l'kortim shebah. No, this
is coming to tell you that even if the little
pieces of the חלתית chilsis are still connected to the leaf. מהו
דתימא ניחוש דילמא מייתי ומערב בה קא משמע לן. mahu d'teima nichush
dilma mayitei u'me'arev bah ka mashma lan.
Maybe I should be concerned that the non-Jew mixed some cut up
חלתית chilsis with the leaves, they weren't like naturally on the leaves.
אשתרוקי הוא דאשתרוק ואתי בהדה. ishtaruki hu d'ishtaruq v'ati bahadah.
No, it's natural that some pieces of the chultit get on the
leaves, you do not have to be concerned that they were added.
Also what would be the motivation to add them? וזיתי גלוסקאות
המגולגלים v'zeitei gluska'ot hamigulgalim and
olives of like a cake that are caked together and that have
been rolled in like a very soft from sitting in like their
juices. פשיטא obviously, what should I be concerned about? לא נצרכה אלא
אף על גב דרפי טובא lo nitzrecha ela af al gav d'rafi
tuva though they're very soft. מהו דתימא חמרא רמי בהו mahu d'teima
chamra rami behu maybe you put wine into them to get them
soft? קא משמע לן הני מחמת משחא הוא דרפי. ka mashma lan
hanei mechamat mishcha hu d'rafi. No, it's because they're sitting in their
oil. רבי יוסי אומר שלחין אסורין. Rabbi Yossi omer shalchin asurin. Rabbi
Yossi says the shalchin olives are forbidden. היכי דמי שלחין? heichi dami
shalchin? What is the shalchin? אמר רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא כל שאוחזו
בידו וגרעינתו נשמטת. amar Rabbi Yossi b'Rabbi Chanina kol she'ochezo b'yado v'gar'inato
nishmitet. You'll see this obviously of some olives that have been sitting
in their juices a lot, if you just hold it in your
hand and the pit just slides right out. That is so soft
that we have to be concerned that wine was added. That's at
least according to רבי יוסי. Okay, החגבים הבאים—so then
it says that the, what do you call it, the locusts that
are in the baskets outside of the store are a problem because
maybe wine was sprinkled on it, but not those that are coming
from the storeroom. תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, we taught: החגבים והכפריסין והקפלוטות.
hachagavim vehakafrisin vehakaplutot.
So all these different things, these are, you know, locust and, what
do you call it, and caper buds and leeks, all those types
of things that maybe they would have added wine to, הבאים מן
האוצר ומן ההפתק, habaim min haotzar umin haheftek, whether they come from
the storehouse or from the, or from the storeroom, you know, ומן
הספינה, umin hasfina,
or from the boat, but any place where they were not being
put out yet to sell, being transported or stored, מותרין. muttarin. Those
are permissible, they would not put wine in it. הנמכרים בקטלוזא, hanimkarim
bekatloza,
but those that are sold in the market, okay, so לפני חנוני
אסורין, lifnei chanvani asurin,
in front of the storekeeper they're forbidden, מפני שמזלף יין עליהן, mipnei
shemezalef yayin aleihen, because he sprinkles wine on them in order to
get them to smell better. וכן יין תפוחים של עובדי כוכבים, vechen
yayin tapuchim shel ovdei kochavim, also when it comes to like apple
cider, is essentially what that sounds like, okay, of non-Jews, do you
have to be concerned that maybe some wine was added? הבאים מן
האוצר ומן ההפתק ומן הסלולה, habaim min haotzar umin haheftek umin hasalula,
if they come from the storehouse or, you know, the storeroom, you
know, or, you know,
or from the basket, even from the basket here, מותרין. muttarin. That's
permissible. So apparently as opposed to the other stuff in the basket
they sprinkled wine, here even in the basket it's permissible. However, הנמכר
בקטלוזא, hanimkar bekatloza, when they bring it to the marketplace, אסור מפני
שמערב בו יין, asur mipnei shemearev bo yayin, because at that stage
they put wine in it. Not exactly clear like why they do
it in the marketplace and not in front of the store. Anyway.
תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, the rabbis taught: פעם אחת חש רבי במיעיו,
paam achat chash Rabbi bimeav, once רבי had a stomach problem. אמר,
he said, כלום יש אדם שיודע יין תפוחים של עובדי כוכבים אסור
או מותר? klum yesh adam sheyodea yayin tapuchim shel ovdei kochavim asur
o muttar? Does anybody know if the apple cider of non-Jews is
forbidden or permissible? Because he felt that that would help him. אמר
לפניו רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי, Amar lefanav Rabbi Yishmael b'Rabbi Yossi, רבי
ישמעאל ברבי יוסי Rabbi Yishmael b'Rabbi Yossi said, פעם אחת חש אבא,
paam achat chash Abba, once my father רבי יוסי had a, had
a pain במיעיו, bimeav, in his stomach, והביאו לו יין תפוחים של
עובדי כוכבים של עין שנה, veheviu lo yayin tapuchim shel ovdei kochavim
shel ayin shana, and they brought apple cider of non-Jews that had
like fermented for seventy years, ונתרפא, venitrape, and it healed him. אמר
לו, Amar lo, so he said him, if so much was in
your hand and you were allowing me to be in pain? So
בדקו ומצאו עובד כוכבים אחד שהיה לו שלש מאות גרבי יין של
תפוחים של עין שנה, badku umatzu oved kochavim echad shehaya lo shelosh
meot garvei yayin shel tapuchim shel ayin shana, they went and they
found a non-Jew who had like three hundred flasks of of of
apple cider, excuse me, of apple cider of
seventy years old, ושתה ונתרפא, veshasa venitrape, and he drank it and
he got better. ואמר, Veamar, and he said, ברוך המקום שמסר עולמו
לשומרים. baruch hamakom shemasar olamo leshomrim. Praised be God who handed over
His world to people, you know, to watchers. Okay, non-Jews, you know,
there's a lot to gain from what they've done in the world.
In the whole, in a whole גמרא here about, you know, being
fears of things of non-Jews or whatever, there's a lot of benefit
out there. Okay, וכן לתרומה, the Mishnah ends. Similarly when it comes
to תרומה, teruma, you know, there's a difference between what's in the
storehouse and what's in front of the store. מאי וכן לתרומה? Mai
vechen litruma? What does this mean? אמר רב ששת, Amar Rav Sheshet,
וכן לכהן החשוד למכור תרומה לשם חולין. vechen lekohen hachashud limkor teruma
leshem chullin. If you have a כהן, kohen, you know, because people
give כהנים kohanim תרומה, teruma but תרומה teruma is less desirable than
חולין chullin because תרומה teruma if you get it טמא, A: it
can only be eaten by כהנים, kohanim, so non-כהנים kohanim wouldn't want
to buy it, and B: if you get it טמא, you're not
allowed to eat it. So let's say there's a כהן kohen that
you suspect, you know, or has reason to suspect, that is selling
his תרומה teruma. and claiming that it's חולין. chullin. You know, so
that's really bad because a Jew would eat it, it'd be a
real major sin if a non-כהן kohen would eat it. לפניו הוא
דאסור, lefanav hu deasur, so then in that case you cannot buy
anything that he's selling like in his store or right in front
of him, אבל הבא מן האוצר ומן ההפתק ומן הסלולה, aval haba
min haotzar umin haheftek umin hasalula, but if it's coming from, you
know, or I guess no, that was the storehouse, directly in front
of him is forbidden. But if it's coming from the storehouse or
from the storeroom or even from like the basket, you know, that
it's in front of the store, in that case מותר, muttar, it's
permissible. Why? אירצויי מירצי, irtzuyei mirtzei, he's afraid, סבר שמעי בי רבנן
ואפסידו לי מינאי. savar shemei bi Rabbanan veafsidu li minai. If it's
coming from a place where there's a lot
of, not wine, excuse me, throw out all of his תרומה. teruma
So if he's just selling a handful of תרומה teruma to you,
okay, you know, even if somebody finds out what are they going
to do? He's not risking anything. But when he's bringing it from
the storehouse or the storeroom or from the store itself, you know,
then he's afraid that he'll be risking all this תרומה and you
do not have to be concerned. הדרן עלך אין מעמידין. Hadran alach
Ein Maamidin. So that is the end of the second פרק, perek,
which is all of these things that we're afraid of supporting the
עבודה זרה avoda zara of non-Jews, you know, interactions with non-Jews, taking
things from non-Jews. from the non-Jewish world that might be non-כשר foods
or might lead to intermarriage or over-socialization, fears of the non-Jews about
rape and murder, all of those interactions which have to do with
non-Jews and the non-Jewish world, not idols, and now in this פרק
perek we turn to idols. כל הצלמים. Kol Hatzlamim. So let's at
least get to the bottom of the page. All
like images אסורין, you know, it might mean like statues, whatever, you
know,
but are forbidden. Why? מפני mipnei
because שנעבדין פעם אחת בשנה shenevadin pa'am achas b'shana דברי רבי מאיר.
divrei Rabbi Meir.
Because at least once in the year, even though normally you would
say, you know, that they are that these that statues are maybe
for aesthetic purposes, you know, they're worshipped once in the year. And
you know it's true, they had all these statues of Roman emperors
and they were part of a like a divine imperial cult and
even if most of the time, you know, maybe people would not
worship them, he said, you know, there'd be at least once each
year, I don't know, maybe it would be the birthday, I don't
know enough about the Roman world, but anyway once a year they
would worship, you know, them. וחכמים אומרים אינו אסור אלא כל שיש
בידו מקל או ציפור או כדור. vachachamim omrim eino assur ela kol
sheyeish beyado makel o tzippor o kaddur. No, an ordinary statue is
not a problem that you're concerned it might be worshipped, only something
that has that's holding something, holding a staff or a bird or
a globe, you know, a sphere. That shows you that that's seen
as as a god. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel
maybe the sphere represents the world. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר אף
כל שיש בידו כל דבר. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer af kol
sheyeish beyado kol davar. Anything holding any statue holding anything represents is
a statue of a god. Okay, let's see what the גמרא says
about this. אי דנעבדי
פעם אחת בשנה מאי טעמייהו דרבנן? Ee dinevadi pa'am achas b'shana mai
ta'amayhu d'rabanan? So the Gemara says the Rabbis did not say they're
not worshipped, the Rabbis just said no, only if it's holding onto
a staff or whatever. So it sounds like they're conceding to Rabbi
Meir that it's worshipped, but they're not bothered with it. Well, how
could that be? If it's worshipped, then how could it not be
a problem? אמר רב יצחק בר יוסף אמר רבי יוחנן במקומו של
רבי מאיר היו עובדין אותה פעם אחת בשנה. Amar Rav Yitzchak bar
Yosef amar Rabbi Yochanan bimkomo shel Rabbi Meir hayu ovdin osa pa'am
achas b'shana. No, everybody agreed that there were a place where they
would worship it once in the year in where Rabbi Meir was.
ורבי מאיר דחייש למיעוטא גזר שאר מקומות אטו אותו מקום. v'Rabbi Meir
d'chaish l'miuta gazar shaar mekomos atu oso makom. Rabbi Meir's concerned about
minority cases. So since there's some places they worship in a year,
he says it's always going to be forbidden. ורבנן דלא חיישי למיעוטא
לא גזרו שאר מקומות אטו אותו מקום. v'rabanan d'lo chaishi l'miuta lo
gazru shaar mekomos atu oso makom. The Rabbis are not concerned with,
you know, with cases of small percentages,
are not concerned with that. Okay, so therefore they all agree on
the מציאות metzius and the question is a legal debate, not a
debate of the reality of what is done.